# **Georgios Vavouliotis**

Curriculum Vitae

☑ gvavou5@gmail.com • • • gvavou5.github.io • in georgios-vavouliotis

#### **Profile**

I earned my diploma on Electrical and Computer Engineering from the National Technical University of Athens (NTUA). Currently, I am a 4th year Ph.D. student in Computer Science at Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya (UPC) and Barcelona Supercomputing Center (BSC-CNS). My supervisors are Dr. Marc Casas Guix from BSC-CNS and Dr. Lluc Alvarez from UPC. Moreover, I collaborate with Prof. Daniel A. Jiménez from Texas A&M University and Prof. Boris Grot from the University of Edinburgh. My research mainly aims at designing intelligent microarchitectural prediction/prefetching mechanisms for the cache and the TLB hierarchy.

### **Areas of (Research) Interest**

Computer Architecture, High Performance Computing (HPC) Systems, Machine Learning for Computer Architecture; identifying and exploiting the predictability of programs to design microarchitectural prefetching/prediction mechanisms for the cache and the TLB hierarchy, improving the cache/TLB management, and leveraging machine learning algorithms to design intelligent microarchitectural components.

#### **Education**

Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya (UPC)

Barcelona

Doctor of Philosophy (Ph.D.)

September 2018-now

Leveraging Artificial Intelligence Algorithms for Hardware Prediction

National Technical University of Athens (NTUA)

**Athens** 

Diploma on Electrical & Computer Engineering, 300 ECTS, GPA: 8.9/10

2012-March 2018

#### Academic Directions.....

- Computer Systems & Software
- Computer Networks and Networks Security
- Signal Processing, Automatic Control and Robotics

#### Diploma Thesis...

Performance Analysis of TLB Prefetching Mechanisms, GPA: 10/10

General Lyceum, Chalkida, Greece

Chalkida

Apolytirion, Top 0.2% in National Qualification Exams, GPA: 19.5/20

2009-2012

## Research Experience

#### Huawei Zurich Research Center

Zurich

**Athens** 

Research Internship Hardware Accelerated Java Garbage Collection November 2021-April 2022

#### **Barcelona Supercomputing Center (BSC-CNS)**

Researcher at Computer Architecture & Operating Systems Group

Barcelona September 2018-now

#### National Technical University of Athens (NTUA)

Research Student at Computer Systems Laboratory (CSLab)

February 2018-July 2018

### **Participation in Projects**

#### SOW 5.3 - Intel and BSC-CNS Collaboration

Barcelona Supercomputing Center (BSC-CNS)

Barcelona

September 2018-now

#### **High Performance Computing VII**

Barcelona Supercomputing Center (BSC-CNS)

Barcelona

September 2018-now

#### **Publications**

- [1] **Georgios Vavouliotis**, Gino Chancon, Lluc Alvarez, Paul V. Gratz, Daniel A. Jiménez, Marc Casas Guix, *Title is not shown for transparency*. Paper is under submission at the 55th IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO), 2022.
- [2] **Georgios Vavouliotis**, Lluc Alvarez, Boris Grot, Daniel A. Jiménez, Marc Casas Guix, *Morrigan: A Composite Instruction TLB Prefetcher*. Proceedings of the 54th IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO), Virtual, October 2021.
- [3] **Georgios Vavouliotis**, Gino Chancon, Lluc Alvarez, Paul V. Gratz, Daniel A. Jiménez, Marc Casas Guix, Leveraging Page Size Information to Enhance Data Cache Prefetching. Poster at the 2021 ACM Summer School on HPC Computer Architectures for Al and Dedicated Applications, Virtual, August 2021. [Best Poster Award]
- [4] **Georgios Vavouliotis**, Lluc Alvarez, Vasileios Karakostas, Konstantinos Nikas, Nectarios Koziris, Daniel A. Jiménez, Marc Casas Guix, *Exploiting Page Table Locality for Agile TLB Prefetching*. Proceedings of the 48th International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA), Virtual, June 2021. Also presented as a *Poster* at the 49th International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA), New York, June 2022.
- [5] **Georgios Vavouliotis**, Lluc Alvarez, Marc Casas Guix, *Pushing the envelope on free TLB prefetching*. Proceedings of the 8th BSC Doctoral Symposium, Virtual, May 2021.
- [6] **Georgios Vavouliotis**, Lluc Alvarez, Daniel A. Jiménez, Marc Casas Guix, *Cost-Effective Instruction TLB Prefetching*. Second Young Architect Workshop (YArch 2020). In conjunction with The 25th ACM International Conference on Architectural Support for Programming Languages and Operating Systems (ASPLOS), Virtual, March 2020.
- [7] **Georgios Vavouliotis**, Goumas Georgios, "Performance Analysis of TLB Prefetching Mechanisms". Book of my diploma thesis.

### **Invited Talks**

Morrigan: A Composite Instruction TLB Prefetcher

Zurich

Huawei Zurich Research Center

December 2021

Morrigan: A Composite Instruction TLB Prefetcher

54th IEEE/ACM International Symposium on Microarchitecture (MICRO)

October 2021

Virtual

Leveraging Page Size Information to Enhance Data Cache Prefetching

Virtual

ACM School on HPC Computer Architectures for AI and Dedicated Applications

August 2021

**Exploiting Page Table Locality for Agile TLB Prefetching**48th International Symposium on Computer Architecture (ISCA)

Virtual June 2021

Pushing the Envelope on Free TLB Prefetching

8th BSC Doctoral Symposium

**Virtual** *May 2021* 

#### **Technical Reviewer for Conferences**

IEEE Supercomputing Conference (SC'21)

° Sub-reviewer

**IEEE Transactions on Computers (2021)** 

Reviewe

18th ACM International Conference on Computing Frontiers (CF'21)

Sub-reviewer

## **Teaching Experience**

Private Tutor Athens

During my Diploma I was giving private lectures to:

2013-2018

#### **Undergraduate students of Computer Science Department**

C programming, Computer Architecture, Operating Systems, Automatic Control

#### **High school students**

Mathematics, Physics

Lab Assistant at National Technical University of Athens (NTUA)

**Athens** C programming 2013-2017

### **Seminars and Training Courses**

#### **Summer Schools**

Participation in accredited Summer Schools (certification provided)

#### HPC Architectures for Artificial Intelligence and Dedicated Applications

Provided by **ACM-Europe**, 17 - 24 July 2019 & 30 - 3 August 2021

#### **Seminars**

Participation in accredited seminars (certification provided)

#### Introduction to Big Data & Practical Data Analytics for Solving Real World Problems

Provided by **PACT BSC-CNS**, February 2021

#### Introduction to Heterogenous Memory Usage

Provided by PACT BSC-CNS, February 2019

#### **Online Courses (MOOCs)**

Courses offered by accredited universities and training programs (certification provided)

#### **Machine Learning**

Provided by Stanford University (Prof. Andrew Ng), May 2018 - July 2018, GPA: 10/10

#### **Advanced Programming with Python**

Provided by Mathesis Online Platform, March 2018 - April 2018, GPA: 10/10

#### **Technical and Personal Skills**

#### Programming Languages

- Advanced knowledge: C
- Working knowledge: C++, Python, Matlab, Assembly (8085, 8086, AVR), SML/NJ, HTML

- Advanced knowledge: Unix Bash, LATEX, SVN
- Working knowledge: Git, CACTI, MS Office

#### Simulators

- Advanced knowledge: ChampSim

#### General Business Skills

- Ability to work with a team
- Very good presentation skills
- Able to write well organized and structured reports

#### **Honors and Awards**

Travel Grant for ISCA'22  O ISCA 2022 Conference	New York 2022
HiPEAC 2021 Paper Award  For the MICRO'21 paper	<b>Virtual</b> 2021
HiPEAC 2021 Paper Award  For the ISCA'21 paper	<b>Virtual</b> 2021
Best Poster Award  2021 ACM School on HPC Computer Architectures for AI and Dedicated Applications	<b>Virtual</b> 2021
2019 FPI Doctoral Fellowship  Funded by Spanish Government (MINECO)	<b>Barcelona</b> 2019-2022
Travel Grant for ASPLOS'20  **Open Conference**  **	Lausanne/Virtual 2020

ASPLOS 2020 Conference

Mathematics Award - National Technical University of Athens (NTUA) **Athens** Excellent marks in all mathematical courses during the first two (2) years. 2014

0	"The Great Moment of Education" Eurobank EFG Scholarship  Highest rank in National Qualifications Exams in my school				
L	.anguages				
0	Greek (Native)	o English	o Italian (Beginner)	<ul><li>Spanish (Beginner)</li></ul>	
F	References				
0	<b>Daniel A. Jiménez</b> <i>Texas A&amp;M University</i>			djimenez.@.cse.tamu.edu	
0	Boris Grot University of Edinburgh			boris.grot@ed.ac.uk	
0	Marc Casas  Universitat Politècnica de Catalunya, Barcelona Supercomputing Center				
0	<b>Lluc Alvarez</b> Universitat Politècnica d	de Catalunya, Barcelo	na Supercomputing Center	lluc.alvarez@bsc.es	